A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Office Files of H. Rowan Gaither FA621
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Office Files of H. Rowan Gaither
1947-1958
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA621
6.16 Cubic Feet
The office files of H. Rowan Gaither cover the years 1947 to 1959, with the bulk of the records dating from 1951 to 1956. The arrangement of the records closely follows an outline that was found enclosed with the files. Presumably the outline described the order in which the files were arranged by Gaither's secretary, Ann Eggars. (Archives was unable to locate this outline as of May 1996.) The files consist mainly of correspondence, reports and notes. Records maintained by Gaither pertaining to the 1949 Study Committee, aka the Gaither Committee, were transferred to the record series for the Study Committee. Some material from the Fund for Adult Education (FAE) folders in series II, boxes 2 and 3, was copied and placed in the F AE grant files, P A51 0-0026 and P A530-0206. Speeches, reports and publications were transferred to their respective collections in the Archives. Transfers are noted on cross-reference sheets in Gaither's records. Appendices to this register list Gaither's speeches and reports and other staff and consultant reports that were transferred to the Ford Foundation Archives' Speech Collection and Unpublished Reports Collection.
Biographical / Historical
H. Rowan Gaither, Ford Foundation President from March 1953 to October 1956, also held the following positions in the Foundation:
• 1948-1950 Director, The Study Committee
• 1951 Associate Director
• 1953-1956 President
• 1953-1960 Trustee
• 1956-1958 Chairman, Board of Trustees
H. Rowan Gaither was born on November 23, 1909. He received his A.B. and LL.B. degrees from the University of California, in 1929 and 1933 respectively. He was admitted to the California bar in 1933.
Before coming to the Ford Foundation, Gaither followed careers in law, banking, and public service. From 1933 to 1936, Gaither served as Special Assistant to the General Counsel of the Farm Credit Administration in Washington.
In 1936 he returned to California where he became partner in the San Francisco law firm of Cooley, Crowley & Supple, later Cooley, Crowley & Gaither. From 1942 to 1945 Gather, on leave from his law firm, served as Assistant Director of the Radiation Laboratory at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He was awarded the Presidential Certificate of Merit for his service in this organization.
In 1948, Gather helped to organize the Rand Corporation, and was appointed Chairman of the Board. In that same year, he was asked by the trustees of the Ford Foundation "to organize and direct a planning study of policy and program for the Foundation." (Report of the Study... 1949, p. 9) Gaither served as Chairman of the Study Committee and Director of the staff of the Committee.
In March 1953, Gaither was appointed President of the Ford Foundation. He served in this position until his resignation on October 1, 1956. On April 22, 1956, Gaither had been named Chairman of the Board of Trustees, a post he held until 1958. Gaither continued to serve as a Ford Foundation trustee until 1960.
During the last year of his life, Gaither was intermittently active in the venture-capital field with the firm of Draper, Gaither and Anderson.
He died on April 6, 1961.
Scope and Contents
The office files of H. Rowan Gaither consist of 5 1/2 linear feet (15 archives boxes) of correspondence, notes and reports. They reflect the early years of the Ford Foundation afar its expansion in 1949 from a local Michigan charity to a national and international philanthropic organization. In 1950, the Report of the Study for the Ford Foundation on Policy and Program was issued by the Study Committee, which was chaired by Gaither.
This report proposed five program areas to be the focal points of the Ford Foundation's operations. In 1950, they were adopted by the Foundation Trustees. They were: Area I: The Establishment of Peace; Area II: The Strengthening of Democracy; Area III: The Strengthening of the Economy; Area IV: Education in a Democratic Society; and Area V: Individual Behavior and Human Relations. The Gaither office files focus on the implementation of these five program areas. The records demonstrate" the influence of, but do not contain, the records of the Study Committee which constitute a separate record sense.
Program Area One - The Establishment of Peace - was intended to foster international understanding, maintain world peace, and combat communist threats to the western world, by strengthening politically and economically the position of the free world, particularly the uncommitted developing countries. The projects were designed to work toward solutions to these problems and fell under the following categories: Overseas Development, Overseas Training and Research, International Affairs, and the Exchange of Persons. Program Area One records contain material relating to the planning and development of these subdivisions. They are particularly valuable in demonstrating the importance that the Foundation placed on gaining greater knowledge of the Soviet Union. The records also include letters from Douglas Ensmiger, the first Ford Foundation representative in India. His correspondence concerns the Foundation's Area One developmental activities in India, which were intended to counterbalance similar assistance from the Soviet Union.
Program Area Two - The Strengthening of Democracy - was designed to safeguard individual civil liberties in a democratic society, and to strengthen the institutions and democratic processes themselves. Program Area Two records include material on the Fund for Adult Education, the Fund for the Republic, and the TV-Radio Workshop.
Program Area Three - The Strengthening of the Economy - was aimed at achieving a productive domestic and world economy in the face of the United States' military and economic commitments abroad and at home. Program Area Three records include material on Resources for the Future.
Program Area Four - Education in a Democratic Society - considered education to be the most important element for the improvement of human welfare and the guarantee of democracy. Program Area Four records include material on the Fund for the Advancement of Education and Intercultural Publications.
Program Area Five - Individual Behavior and Human Relations - addressed the need for knowledge of human behavior and for its application on all program areas of the Foundation. Program Area Five records include material on a controversial grant to the University of Chicago Law School. One purpose of the project was to "study the actual operation of the jury system". In 1954, as part of the research, the deliberations of a jury in Wichita, Kansas were recorded without the jurors' knowledge. Public outrage resulted and eventually the case was investigated by the United States Senate Sub-Committee on Internal Security. The Ford Foundation received much criticism for having funded the project. This occurrence raised basic policy questions regarding the Foundation's relationship to its grantees, and the limits of Foundation accountability to, and responsibility for, grantee action. The incident and the questions it raised are well documented in the Area Five series.
The Ford Foundation itself came under Congressional investigation during the 1950s. In the wake of the Cox Committee (House Select Committee to Investigate Tax-Exempt Foundations and Comparable Organizations)and Reece Committee (House Special Committee to Investigate Tax-Exempt Foundations) hearings, the Foundation's Board and officers recognized the need to educate the public about the benefits of organized philanthropy and commissioned a study on this subject. The background material for the study is contained in the Program Area Two series. Gather's files on the Cox and Reece Committees are located in Series VI, Administration, sub series on Public Relations (boxes 11 and 12).
Series VI, Administration, is comprised of five subseries: Personnel; Grant Policies and Procedures; Organization and Administration; Financial and Legal; and Public Relations. The records in this series, especially the Organization and Administration subseries, provide a good source for researchers investigating such topics as institution building and organization and management. This sub series draws on and applies the guidelines set forth by the Study Committee's report. Many reports from this sub series have been transferred to the Archives' Reports Collection. The remaining material complements the reports. The Administration series also contains a file on the financial relationship between the Ford Foundation and the Ford Motor Company during the years 1947 to 1956.
As a whole, Gaither's office files document the Foundation's unique role in the history of philanthropy, conveying the sense of limitless possibility that permeated the Foundation in its early years. They reflect the Foundation's resolve to act as an institution dedicated to promoting the public well-being and contributing to the solution of problems both national and international in scope, completely separate from the United States government.
Separated Materials
Appendix A, B, and C describe materials removed from the original collection by Ford Foundation staff.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Arrangement
The office files of H. Rowan Gaither, Office of the President, are divided into eight subject series. Although Gaither did not become President until 1953, the records document his Foundation activities from 1950 to 1959, with the bulk of the records from 1951 to 1956, and include some earlier material, which he inherited from his predecessor, Paul Hoffman. The series are:
I. Area One: The Establishment of Peace II. Area Two: The Strengthening of Democracy III. Area Three: The Strengthening of the Economy IV. Area Four: Education in a Democratic Society V. Area Five: Individual Behavior and Human Relations VI. Administration VII. Non-Program Suggestions VIII. Ford Motor Company Reports
Series I: Area One files (1951-1956). Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject.
Series ll: Area Two files (1949-1956). Four subseries, as follows:
• Program Material (1949-1956). Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject. • The Fund for Adult Education (1951-1956). Arranged chronologically. • The Fund for the Republic (1951-1956). Arranged chronologically. • TV-Radio Workshop (1953-1956). Arranged chronologically.
Series III: Area Three files (1951-1956). Two subseries, as follows:
• Program Material (1951-1956). Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject. • Resources for the Future (1953-1956). Arranged chronologically.
Series IV: Area Four files (1951-1956). Three subseries, as follows:
• Program Material (1951-1956). Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject. • The Fund for the Advancement of Education (1951-1956). Arranged chronologically. • Intercultural Publications (1953-1955). Arranged chronologically.
Series V: Area Five files (1951-1956). Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject.
Series VI: Administration files (1947-1958). .Five subseries, each arranged chronologically, as follows:
• Personnel (1951-1956) • Grant Policies and Procedures (1952-1956) • Organization and Administration (1951-1956) • Financial and Legal (1947-1956) • Public Relations (1949-1959)
Series VlI: Non-Program Suggestions (1952-1956). The material consists of program proposals which were not funded, and funded projects that did not fall under the usual program areas. Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject.
Series VIII: Ford Motor Company Reports (1946-1955). Annual and financial reports arranged chronologically.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Completion of a use agreement is required prior to providing scholarly access. See RAC Head of Reference (or applicable designee) for details.
- Area One: The Establishment of Peace, I
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject.
  - CIA [Central Intelligence Agency], 1951 April - 1951 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes correespondence between H. Rowan Gaither, Bernard L. Gladieux, and John B. Howard re: "whether the Ford Foundation could act as a channel for the expenditure of CIA funds". Also includes notes from a April 3, 1951 conference with Walter Bedell "Beetle" Smith and Allen Dulles re: possible projects.
  - Dubridge Trip, 1951 August (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - European Program, 1951 May - 1956 April (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General, 1950 - 1951 November (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - General, 1952 January - 1953 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - General, 1954 January - 1955 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - General, 1956 January - 1956 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - General, 1956 April - 1956 July (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Totalitarian Governments Study, 1951 November (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Area Two: The Strengthening of Democracy, II
  - Program Material, 1949-1956; A
    - Civil Liberties, 1951 August - 1952 March (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Civil Liberties, 1952 April - 1953 March (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Commission on Public Service, 1953 March - 1953 July (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - General, 1949 February - 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - General, 1952 June - 1954 July (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Government Services, 1950 - 1952 May (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Government Services, 1952 June - 1954 August (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Hospital Program, 1955 December - 1956 June (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Political Process, 1952 September (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Race Relations and Minorities, 1951 April - 1952 April (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Security-Freedom, 1951 June - 1955 October (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Seminar on Freedom, 1951 June - 1951 August (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - The Study of Philanthropy, [n.d.] - 1955 November (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - The Study of Philanthropy, 1955 December - 1956 November (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - The Fund for Adult Education, 1951-1956; B
    Arranged chronologically.
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1951 February - 1951 October (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1951 November - 1952 December (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1953 January - 1953 July (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1953 August - 1953 December (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1954 January (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1954 February - 1954 May (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1954 June (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - The Fund for Adult Education (FAE), 1954 July - 1956 September (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Joint Commttee on Adult Education, Study., 1954 August - 1954 December (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Joint Commttee on Adult Education, Study., 1955 January - 1955 October (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Joint Commttee on Adult Education, Study., 1955 October - 1956 January (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - The Fund for the Republic, 1951-1956; C
    - The Fund for the Republic, 1952 September - 1953 June (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - The Fund for the Republic, 1953 August - 1955 September (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - The Fund for the Republic, 1955 October - 1955 December (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - The Fund for the Republic, 1956 January - 1956 August (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - TV-Radio Workshop, 1953-1956; D
    - TV-Radio Workshop, 1953 April - 1953 October (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - TV-Radio Workshop, 1953 November - 1953 December (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - TV-Radio Workshop, 1954 March - 1955 April (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - TV-Radio Workshop, 1955 June - 1956 June (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Area Three: The Strenghtening of the Economy, III
  - Program Material, 1951-1956; A
    - Business Administration, 1952 June - 1953 November (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Cambridge Institute, 1951 February - 1953 March (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Conservation-Resources Development, 1952 March - 1953 January (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - General, 1951 January - 1952 September (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - General, 1953 January - 1956 January (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Labor-Management, 1951 May - 1952 January (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Resources for the Future, 1953-1956; B
    - Resources for the Future, 1953 March - 1953 September (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - Resources for the Future, 1953 October - 1953 December (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Resources for the Future, 1954 Januray - 1956 April (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Area Four: Education in a Democratic Society, IV
  - Program Material, 1951-1956; A
    - College Grants-General Support, 1955 April - 1955 December (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - College Grants-General Support, 1956 March - 1956 August (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - General, 1950 - 1952 February (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - General, 1952 May - 1955 October (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - General, 1956 January - 1956 July (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - General, 1956 August - 1956 October (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - Leadership, 1951 May - 1955 April (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - National Scholarship Program, 1955 March - 1955 May (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - National Scholarship Program, 1955 June - 1955 October (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1951-1956; B
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), [n.d.] - 1951 November (Box 5, Folder 61)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1952 January - 1953 August (Box 5, Folder 62)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1953 September - 1953 December (Box 5, Folder 63)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1954 January (Box 5, Folder 64)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1954 February - 1954 June (Box 6, Folder 65)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1954 July - 1954 September (Box 6, Folder 66)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1954 October - 1954 November (Box 6, Folder 67)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE), 1954 December - 1956 May (Box 6, Folder 68)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE) - Educational TV, 1955 November - 1956 November (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE) - Center for Contemporary Thought, 1953 April - 1954 January (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - Intercultural Publications, 1953-1955; C
    - Intercultural Publications, 1953 February - 1953 June (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Intercultural Publications, 1953 July - 1953 December (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Intercultural Publications, 1954 February - 1955 January (Box 6, Folder 73)
- Area Five: Individual Behavior and Human Relations, V
  - Program Material - General, [n.d.] - 1951 May (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Program Material - General, 1951 May - 1951 December (Box 7, Folder 75)
  - Program Material - General, 1952 January - 1957 May (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - Governent Contract Research, 1951 June (Box 7, Folder 77)
  - Hutchins, Robert, 1954 March - 1954 April (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Jury Project /University of Chicago, 1955 October (Box 7, Folder 79)
- Administration, VI
  Five subseries, each arranged chronologically.
  - Personnel, 1951-1956; A
    - Consultants, 1953 June - 1956 March (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Insurance and Medical Coverage, 1954 February - 1955 September (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Personnel Policies, 1951 November - 1955 February (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Personnel Reports, 1952 April - 1954 April (Box 8, Folder 83)
    - Personnel Reports, 1954 May - 1955 May (Box 8, Folder 84)
    - Personnel Reports, 1955 August - 1955 December (Box 8, Folder 85)
    - Personnel Reports, 1952 April - 1955 September (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Grant Policies and Procedures, 1952-1956; B
    - Accumulation of Income, 1953 May - 1956 May (Box 8, Folder 87)
    - Invasion of Principal, [n.d.] - 1956 September (Box 8, Folder 88)
    - President's Discretionary Fund and Officers' Grants, 1952 July - 1954 April (Box 8, Folder 89)
    - President's Discretionary Fund and Offcers' Grants, 1954 May - 1955 March (Box 8, Folder 90)
    - Program Action Forms, 1955 April - 1956 December (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Program Action Forms, 1956 January - 1956 October (Box 8, Folder 92)
    - Welfare Activities, 1954 June - 1955 March (Box 8, Folder 93)
  - Organization and Administration, 1951-1956; C
    - Administration, 1953 August - 1955 May (Box 8, Folder 94)
    - Administrative Assignments, 1953 April - 1956 August (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Central Secretariat, 1954 March - 1956 October (Box 8, Folder 96)
    - Division of Responsibilities: Relationship of Funds, 1951 - 1952 May (Box 8, Folder 97)
    - Division of Responsibilities: Relationship of Funds, 1952 June - 1954 March (Box 8, Folder 98)
    - Functions of Board Chairman, 1954 January - 1954 December (Box 9, Folder 99)
    - Functions of Board Chairman, 1955 August - 1958 January (Box 9, Folder 100)
    - Gould, Laurence, 1954 May - 1957 May (Box 9, Folder 101)
    - Officers' Meetings, 1954 October - 1955 September (Box 9, Folder 102)
    - Organization and Administration - General, 1951 April - 1951 November (Box 9, Folder 103)
    - Organization and Administration - General, 1952 April - 1952 December (Box 9, Folder 104)
    - Organization and Administration - General, 1953 January - 1953 May (Box 9, Folder 105)
    - Organization and Administration - General, 1953 June - 1953 October (Box 9, Folder 106)
    - Organization and Administration - General, 1954 January - 1956 (Box 9, Folder 107)
    - Program Committee, 1954 January - 1954 November (Box 9, Folder 108)
    - Program Planning, 1950 December - 1955 August (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - Program Review and Projection, 1953 March - 1954 August (Box 9, Folder 110)
    - Role of Trustees, 1954 October - 1957 April (Box 9, Folder 111)
    - Staff Meetings, 1953 July - 1953 December (Box 9, Folder 112)
    - Stratton, Julius, 1955 December - 1957 June (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Financial and Legal, 1947-1956; D
    - Accounting Practices, 1953 May - 1955 September (Box 10, Folder 114)
    - Budget, 1952 December - 1953 December (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Budget, 1954 January - 1956 August (Box 10, Folder 116)
    - Financial and Legal - General, 1953 April - 1956 January (Box 10, Folder 117)
    - Ford Motor Co. - Correspondence, 1947 November - 1953 March (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Ford Motor Co. - Correspondence, 1955 February - 1955 June (Box 10, Folder 119)
    - Ford Motor Co. - Correspondence, 1955 November (Box 10, Folder 120)
    - Ford Motor Co. - Correspondence, 1955 December (Box 10, Folder 121)
    - Ford Motor Co. - Correspondence, 1956 January - 1956 April (Box 10, Folder 122)
    - Ford Motor Co. - Correspondence, 1956 May - 1956 August (Box 10, Folder 123)
    - Investments, 1951 May - 1956 February (Box 10, Folder 124)
  - Public Relations, 1949-1959; E
    - American Legion, 1953 September (Box 11, Folder 125)
    - Annual Report 1953, 1953 March - 1954 December (Box 11, Folder 126)
    - Annual Report 1954, 1954 October - 1955 June (Box 11, Folder 127)
    - Annual Report 1955, 1955 December - 1956 March (Box 11, Folder 128)
    - Cox Committee, 1952 March - 1952 August (Box 11, Folder 129)
    - Cox Committee, 1952 September - 1952 December (Box 11, Folder 130)